Finding Aid for Hazel Marie Losh papers, 1870s-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hazel Marie Losh papers 1870s-1978
Losh, Hazel Marie, 1898-1978.
2 linear feet.
861079 Aa 2
Professor of astronomy at the University of Michigan, friend and booster of U-M athletics and athletes; correspondence, speeches, class materials, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from the estate of Hazel Losh (donor no. 6254 ) in 1978.
The collection is open to research.
Hazel M. Losh was born August 28, 1898 in Blanchester, Ohio. She was educated at Ohio Wesleyan (B.A., 1920) and the University of Michigan (M.A., 1922; Ph.D. in Astronomy, 1924). She began her career as an instructor in astronomy at Smith College (1924-1925) and with the Mt. Wilson Observatory Solar Department (1925-1927). She came to the University of Michigan Department of Astronomy in 1927 as instructor. She would eventually work her way up to full professor in 1965. She retired in 1969 and died October 5, 1978.
Professor Losh was a popular undergraduate teacher. Many of the University's student athletes took her introductory course in astronomy. In addition, she gave many public lectures as well as a monthly radio program on astronomy for the U-M's public radio station.
The collection is comprised of three series: Correspondence, course materials, and other papers; Photographs; and Sound Recording. The photographs are of Losh family members, photos relating to University of Michigan athletics and other interests. There are also photos of Hazel Losh teaching in the classroom. The Sound Recording is of Professor Thomas Slavens interviewing Professor Losh about her life and career. A transcript has been made of this recording.
Subjects:
Astronomy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Losh, Hazel Marie, 1898-1978.; Oral histories.; Phi Beta Kappa. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Losh, Hazel Marie, 1898-1978.; Losh family.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; Women.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Losh, Hazel Marie, 1898-1978.; University of Michigan--History.
Contributors:
Slavens, Thomas P., 1928-
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence, course materials, and other papers
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated and 1921-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1924 (Box 1)
    - 1925-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Papers re. Ann Arbor residences (910 E. Huron St. and 844 E. University Ave.) (Box 1)
  - Transcript of interview with Hazel Losh conducted by Thomas Slavens, ca. 1976 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Publications, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Speech notes, Astronomy and Sports (on cards), 1 envelope (Box 1)
  - Speeches and speech notes (astronomy and sports) (Box 1)
  - Student papers
    - "History of Astronomy" (in verse) by Seibert S. Sproull, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "History of Astronomy" (in verse and illustrated) by Robert Wild, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "History of Astronomy" (in verse) by Tom Dudley, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Teaching appointments (Box 1)
  - Student papers and examinations (sample) (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Activities, interests
    - Athletes and coaches (Box 2)
    - Dinners and Awards (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Observatories (Box 2)
    - Professional Groups (Box 2)
    - Residences (Box 2)
    - Sporting Events (Box 2)
    - Trip to Blanchester, Ohio (birthplace), August 1974 (Box 2)
    - With Tom Harmon (Box 2)
  - Family
    - Aunts and Uncles (Box 2)
    - Clara Belle Losh, cousin (Box 2)
    - Group photos, black and white (Box 2)
    - Group photos, color (Box 2)
    - Hazel M. Losh and others, black and white (Box 2)
    - Hazel M. Losh and others, color (Box 2)
    - Mabel (May Belle ?) Losh, sister (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Mary Losh (mother) (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Mary Losh (mother) and Hazel M. Losh (Box 2)
    - Relatives and Friends, unidentified (Box 2)
  - Personal
    - Adult (Box 2)
    - Color photos (Box 2)
    - Graduation, Ohio Wesleyan University, 1920 (Box 2)
    - Later years (Box 2)
    - Youth (Box 2)
    - Negatives (Box 2)
  - Album presented at tea honoring Professor Hazel Marie Losh, April 11, 1968 (Box 2)
- Sound recording
  - Interview conducted by Professor Thomas Slavens, circa. 1976 (Box 2)
    (transcript of interview located in box 1)